<!DOCTYPE tripset SYSTEM "file:birdwalker.dtd"><tripset><trip name="From Field List 1" date="1996-02-10" leader="Steve Shunk?" url="" filename-stem="1996-02-10-from-field-list-1"><notes><p>We think this might be the trip we took with Jacques and Marianne</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="From Field List 2" date="1996-02-11" leader="Mary and Bill?" url="" filename-stem="1996-02-11-from-field-list-2"></trip>
<trip name="From Field List 3" date="1996-03-15" leader="Mary and Bill?" url="" filename-stem="1996-03-15-from-field-list-3"></trip>
<trip name="Lunch with Andria and Sumit" date="1996-07-06" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1996-07-06-lunch-with-andria-and-sumit"></trip>
<trip name="Camping with Ken" date="1996-10-26" leader="Mary, Bill, and Ken" url="" filename-stem="1996-10-26-camping-with-ken"><notes><p>We encountered an expert birder (possibly a former PRBO volunteer), who showed us lots of passerines, especially warblers.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="1996-10-27" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1996-10-27-sunday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Weekend at Chez Frankel" date="1997-02-06" leader="" url="" filename-stem="1997-02-06-weekend-at-chez-frankel"><notes><p>We also saw Sea Otter and Elephant Seal.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Point Reyes Expedition" date="1997-05-24" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1997-05-24-point-reyes-expedition"><notes><p>We walked around in shorts, and got sunburned like crazy. We walked through cow pastures, and down a shallow, sandy descent through the trees.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Bike Ride" date="1997-10-15" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1997-10-15-bike-ride"><notes><p>two TV's were stopped in the path in front of me, eating off a bird carcass. They kept flying off and landing further in front of me.</p><p></p><p>three terns were screaming and angrily dive bombing a seemingly oblivious cormorant who sat quitely in the water. When it flew off ten minutes later, the screaming stopped.</p><p></p><p>the curlew/whimbrels were just standing the road looking confused, yards from the water.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Wings over Ed Levin" date="1997-10-19" leader="Steve Shunk" url="" filename-stem="1997-10-19-wings-over-ed-levin"><notes><p>We went with Steve to Ed Levin State Park as part of a wild bird center trip -- Shrike, Meadowlark, Northern Harrier, Say's Pheobe, White-tailed Kite, Black Pheobe, Downy Woodpecker</p><p></p><p>Then in the afternoon we went out with him privately to coyote creek riparian station and its pond -- merlin, peregrine falcon, sandpiper, shovelers, ring-billed gull, mew gull (?), meadowlark, TV, red-tailed hawk, golden-crown sparrow.</p><p></p><p>We lost our peterson's guide, but perhaps the national geographic guide is better? Bought a new binocular strap.</p><p></p><p>Spent too much time looking for relevant on-line birding resources.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="1997-10-26" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1997-10-26-sunday-stroll"><notes><p>We parked at the south end of the Charleston Slough parking lot, walked around the northern end of the pond, went a short distance out onto the slough, then back for one last look at the pond. I was alerted by the BIRDWEST mailing list to the presence of a RED-NECKED GREBE at the pond, and had found it two days earlier. We found it again today at the end of our walk. We also found a BLUE-WINGED TEAL following a tip from a fellow birder. In a tableau of teals and ducks together, we were reminded how much smaller teals are than ducks. Also at the end of our walk we saw a BARROW'S GOLDENEYE across the pond. This sighting was confirmed Monday on BIRDWEST.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Wings over Oregon 1" date="1997-11-10" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1997-11-10-wings-over-oregon-1"><notes><p>Colusa Wildlife Refuge offered a charming driving tour of what I presume are irrigation channels, ponds, and fields of cattails. The birds were quite acclimated to cars, but flushed immediately when I got out of the car to retrieve something from the trunk. The new binoculars worked out very well. I didn't need them to see the pheasants, though -- they stood right on the road and stared at me. I saw something that looked like a Curlew dipped in coal dust, and decided it must have been some kind of Ibis, although the light wasn't good enough to see any color details.</p><p></p><p>A short drive along the river brought me to Gray Lodge Wildlife Refuge, although the number of hunters there made the term "refuge" seem a little funny. Apparently, there's a lot of people out there who think it's fun to camp out in a muddy camping lot on a Monday night in order to put their names in a lottery to earn the right to wander around in the marsh and shoot birds. Myself, I prefer to gaze on them from the comfort of my car, although these birds were a lot more skittish, and even hiding in the car didn't stop them from running away. In addition to the plentiful ducks I expected, there was a lovely two-point white-tailed deer, and some kind of marine mammal in a pond. I heard reports from two fellow birders that the Sacramento Wildlife Refuge had lots of vultures and geese, which I didn't get to see today -- perhaps I'll stop there on the way back.</p><p></p><p>The region containing these two refuges reminded me a lot of central Illinois. Very flat, roads running in straight lines, most of the land consumed by agriculture. Except that you'd see a flooded field with SEAGULLS sitting in it. That seemed really out of place!</p><p></p><p>On the way back to I5, I had the distinct pleasure of crossing the Princeton Ferry -- A platform the size of a large houseboat that pulls itself across the 50 feet of the sluggish Sacramento River for a mere 50 cents. Why not a bridge? I can only assume the river isn't always so sluggish, and must vary a lot in depth. Either that or Glenn County doesn't have much of a tax base for infrastructure.</p><p></p><p>The drive up to Weed was uneventful. I did pass by an unlit sign saying "chains required next two miles" and other sign saying "summit 3,900 feet" that reminded me that I'm _not_ in Illinois.</p><p></p><p>Tomorrow -- a marsh just north of here on I97 that is supposed to have lots of raptors and geese and stuff.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Wings over Oregon 2" date="1997-11-11" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1997-11-11-wings-over-oregon-2"><notes><p>Departing from Weed, CA on I95, I had lovely views of the scenery on my way up to Butte Valley. At BV I did another driving tour, listening to the distant sounds of honking swans from across the lake. There were few other sounds, it was so quiet. On the other side of the road the buffleheads spooked easily, fluttering further down a narrow channel. On my way out of the area I drove within a few yards of a large raptor perched on the side of the road. It might have been an immature eagle of some kind, but I didn't think the beak was big enough. I'm hoping to learn more about raptors on this trip.</p><p></p><p>I then pretty much drove straght to Sisters, stopping at the occassional gas station on I97, which is definitely a logger's highway, not a birder's highway. Steve and I ran some errands, had dinner, and sat at his apartment until late looking at his latest photographic endeavors. I'm staying at the lovely home of Dottie Yurgel, who volunteers at the chamber of commerce. She pointed out that The Tick probably doesn't have any anti-freeze and made space in her garage so the radiator might not freeze solid overnight. Winter, Bill, they have Winter here. Duh. We bought some anti-freeze, I hope I'll get to put it in the car tomorrow.</p><p></p><p>Tomorrow's plan: Visit Bend's sewage treatment pond, then drive the McKenzie pass scenic tour in the afternoon.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Wings over Oregon 3" date="1997-11-12" leader="Bill and Steve" url="" filename-stem="1997-11-12-wings-over-oregon-3"><notes><p>This morning's trip to the Bend Wastewater Treatment Plant was very rewarding. We stood quite still for a long time, overlooking a pond with hundreds of ducks. With little ambient noise, I was able to hear the sound of wind whistling through duck feathers as they swooped into a landing at high speed. I spotted a Merlin, which we later decided is a male Tiega variant. As we were packing everything into the car, Steve spotted a raptor way up high that we decided must be an immature bald eagle. Fantastic.</p><p></p><p>This afternoon I did the McKenzie pass scenic route. The pass itself was otherworldly. Shrouded in fog, the snow covered trees stood watch over the barren, hulking mass of lava boulders. The spindliness of the trees, the absence of other humans, the fog drifting over the terrain and the utter quiet made me feel like the last person on earth. I didn't see a single mountain peek through the fog (and there should have been many), but I loved it. I hope the pictures might come out. I also stopped by some waterfalls and greeted them. The Tick rolls bravely toward it's 100,000 mile mark, currently at 99907!</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Wings over Oregon 4" date="1997-11-13" leader="Bill and Steve" url="" filename-stem="1997-11-13-wings-over-oregon-4"><notes><p>We had an early morning trip to the Haystack reservoir north of Bend. Steve Shunk and I were accompanied by Steven Holt,  wildlife photographer and his dog Coot. Mr. Holt and Coot car camp from a Geo Metro that has seen better days. Holt is a charming birder, knowledgeable but not overpowering. He worked at a natural history museum in Philly, curating a collection of bird photographs. I am tempted to order one of his enlargements, perhaps one of his black oystercatcher shots. Along the way to the reservoir we stopped at a river crossing, where we saw the owl sitting quietly in a tree near the river. The reservoir was very foggy and cold. Steve peered at ducks through the scope at maximum magnification, I looked through it and saw only grey. We saw some excellent raptors on power poles along the highway. We saw a dead cow lying on its side in a field, with legs and udders firmly outstretched. We saw ravens feeding on a dead deer.</p><p></p><p>On the way home, The Tick rolled over 100,000 miles. And still going strong. Particularly with over 1/2 a gallon of new anti-freeze in its system. Spoon!</p><p></p><p>In the afternoon, I bought wool socks and pens. In the evening I did my crossword puzzle while attending Steve's Community Feedback Forum.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Wings over Oregon 5" date="1997-11-14" leader="Bill and Steve" url="" filename-stem="1997-11-14-wings-over-oregon-5"><notes><p>After more fooling around with The Tick (turns out the guy didn't fully retighten the valve at the bottom of the radiator), Steve and I finally got underway at around noon. We drove past the town of Brothers (town for sale) and stopped for lunch at  Halton Station, where they have coyote pelts for sale, a sheet listing the bail amounts for different traffic offenses, and a bumper sticker near the restroom that says "paper products are no longer available, just wipe your ass on a spotted owl." I ate a grilled chese sandwitch and watched Quincy reruns on satellite TV. The state trooper driving the late model white Camaro stopped in for hot chocolate.</p><p></p><p>By then the terrain was already High Desert, as though I was living in a Tony Hillerman novel. It was expansive, desolate, beautiful. We did a raptor count while driving, and then started another list once we got inside the Refuge. We're spending the night in Frenchglen at a bed and breakfast run by Steve's friend. Just outside of Frenchglen we stopped at the Buena Vista scenic overlook for some experimental pictures of the (nearly) full moon peeking through the clouds and shining on the marshes. As the moon reappeared from behind the clouds, it seemed to shine as bright as the noontime sun, accompanied by a three-part invention -- the mooing of grumpy cattle, the honking of irrascible geese, and mysterious yowling of coyotes. Something (probably a deer) was walking around in the water, splashing as it went. Sillouettes of ducks crossed through the moon's reflection on the water. A beautiful evening.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Wings over Oregon 6" date="1997-11-15" leader="Bill and Steve" url="" filename-stem="1997-11-15-wings-over-oregon-6"><notes><p>This morning we wandered around the Palm Springs campground and hiked up to the top of a butte, a tremendously warming exercise. As we were finishing up the sun hit the bottom of the canyon and the trees really came alive. After a hearty breakfast of pancakes, we zoomed up north and started slowly down the central patrol road, stopping frequently. We braved a very windy levy for looks at two kinds of swans. We frowned at idiots who were harrassing a great horned owl. After grabbing our snack food bag, we headed up to the top of Steen mountain, which was clearly covered with snow. We saw Snow Buntings, a life bird for Steve and a really cool find. We didn't get to the top of the mountain due to snow drifts, but we took some excellent pictures and generally had an adventure.</p><p></p><p>At dinner I met Steve's friend Terry, who is a remarkable man. A very large, thoughtful man who has been a bar bouncer, professional trapper, policeman, professional hunter, and employee of the malheur wildlife refuge. Now he roams the west, camping and taking wildlife photographs to turn into greeting cards. I hope to get some of them.Terry is a native of Oregon, and has very strong views about government bureaucracy, cowboys, resistance to change, mosquitos, and drinking. I'm so glad I got to meet him.</p><p></p><p>Mary says on the phone that she put down a deposit on a rental house in Santa Clara. I hope we won't be let down.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Wings over Oregon 7" date="1997-11-16" leader="Bill and Steve" url="" filename-stem="1997-11-16-wings-over-oregon-7"><notes><p>Our last day on the refuge started with coffe with Terry, followed by more pancakes -- this time with blueberries. We drove north on the Central Patrol Road, and I thought I saw an owl in a large tree right near the road. Just as Steve was stopping the truck we flushed an adult Bald Eagle and watched it fly off. Astounding. From the closed refuge headquarters Steve saw a white pelican amongst the far-off swans. A Stellar's Jay, dubbed the accidental resident, was still at HQ, despite not being on the official refuge bird list. I got a good long look at a Prairie Falcon while Steve was mapping out Burns's sewage ponds for a book entitled "Birding the Sewage Ponds of Oregon." I'm not making this up!</p><p></p><p>After lunch we headed for home, and I left from Steve's house for Klamath Falls at 7:00pm. There was some excitement caused by snow on the road, but I arrived here safely. I hope to leave early tomorrow and hit the Sacramento refuge before heading home.</p><p></p><p>Malheur Refuge total, 66 species. Trip total so far, 80 species.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Wings over Oregon 8" date="1997-11-17" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1997-11-17-wings-over-oregon-8"><notes><p>I left Klamath Falls shrouded in fog, and stayed in fog until just across the California border when I burst into the clear just in time for a spectacular view of Mt. Shasta. After getting down into the Central Valley, I indulged in two detours. The first was to the Coleman National Fish Hatchery, which wasn't too exciting in its own right, but had some excellent birding along the way, including a huge clump of Turkey Vultures and some nice woodpeckers. The second detour was the Sacramento National Wildlife Refuge, which turned out to be an excellent place to see all the geese I didn't see up in Oregon. There were thousands of geese and ducks to see from the Auto Tour route, and two very large flocks of shorebirds that wheeled around in unison and landed each time right underneath the setting sun. They were probably Dowitchers, but I couldn't tell.</p><p></p><p>Overall, I saw around 100 species of birds, including 67 in the Malheur refuge. Of these, 24 were species I had never seen before. I hope to see all of them again, and to recognize them when I do. What a trip!</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1997-12-12" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1997-12-12-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1997-12-15" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1997-12-15-lunchtime-walk"><notes><p>I was surprised to see a turkey vulture flying around the slough so persistently and even landing on one of the little sand bars. There was a kingfisher on the mast of one of the rental sailboats. I saw sixteen or seventeen night herons sleeping, and some probably juvenilles among them.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1998-01-02" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-01-02-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1998-01-13" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-01-13-lunchtime-walk"><notes><p>Wow, I stumbled across possibly the highest tide of the year. I saw the rare and elusive black rail, which Mary didn't see until the same high tide, three years later.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="1998-01-18" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-01-18-sunday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1998-01-23" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-01-23-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Coastal Expedition" date="1998-01-24" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-01-24-coastal-expedition"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1998-01-28" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-01-28-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Weekend Trip" date="1998-01-31" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-01-31-weekend-trip"></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="1998-02-15" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-02-15-sunday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1998-02-18" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-02-18-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1998-02-24" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-02-24-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Saturday Stroll" date="1998-02-28" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-02-28-saturday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1998-03-03" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-03-03-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Saturday Stroll" date="1998-03-14" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-03-14-saturday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Visiting Ran and Laura" date="1998-04-20" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-04-20-visiting-ran-and-laura"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1998-05-12" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-05-12-lunchtime-walk"><notes><p>No rails, no pelicans, no kestrels. A crow nest near the new boat dock.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="1998-05-17" leader="" url="" filename-stem="1998-05-17-sunday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1998-05-19" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-05-19-lunchtime-walk"><notes><p>Talked with a photographer who had an enormous lens pointed at a Black-neck stilt nest. Never saw anything so awkward as a stilt trying to settle down on to a nest. The photographer claims that Clapper Rails are nothing but low-down double-crossin' egg stealers. The nerve. Got to compare Dowitchers and Godwits in the same scope view. Got to look at a nearby Tern for a long time, but didn't see black going down the back of its neck as the field guide demanded.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Playing Hooky with John" date="1998-06-03" leader="Bill and John" url="" filename-stem="1998-06-03-playing-hooky-with-john"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1998-06-12" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-06-12-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1998-06-23" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-06-23-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Saturday Stroll" date="1998-06-27" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-06-27-saturday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Cape Cod Family Trip" date="1998-07-23" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-07-23-cape-cod-family-trip"></trip>
<trip name="Pre-Ashland" date="1998-08-01" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-08-01-pre-ashland"></trip>
<trip name="Anniversary Pelagic Trip" date="1998-08-29" leader="Debra Shearwater" url="" filename-stem="1998-08-29-anniversary-pelagic-trip"><notes><p>Mammals:</p><p></p><p>Short-beak (common) Dolphin</p><p>Dahl's Porpoise</p><p>Humpback Whale</p><p>Sea Lion</p><p>Sea Otter</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Anniversary Slough Trip" date="1998-08-30" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-08-30-anniversary-slough-trip"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1998-09-01" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-09-01-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="1998-10-18" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-10-18-sunday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1998-10-23" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-10-23-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="1998-10-25" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-10-25-sunday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1998-11-24" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-11-24-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Thanksgiving Trip 1" date="1998-11-27" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-11-27-thanksgiving-trip-1"></trip>
<trip name="Thanksgiving Trip 2" date="1998-11-28" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-11-28-thanksgiving-trip-2"><notes><p>The entries for this day of this trip are probably just the new ones not seen on the day before. We apparently didn't record repeat sightings on this trip</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Thanksgiving Trip 3" date="1998-11-29" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-11-29-thanksgiving-trip-3"><notes><p>The entries for this day of this trip are probably just the new ones not seen on the day before. We apparently didn't record repeat sightings on this trip</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1998-12-07" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-12-07-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1998-12-17" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1998-12-17-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1999-01-07" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-01-07-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1999-01-28" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-01-28-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Birding with Hilary 1" date="1999-01-30" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-01-30-birding-with-hilary-1"></trip>
<trip name="Birding with Hilary 2" date="1999-01-31" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-01-31-birding-with-hilary-2"></trip>
<trip name="Central Valley Trip" date="1999-02-07" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-02-07-central-valley-trip"><notes><p>Mary and Bill, Katie and Kevin go to the Audubon blind for watching Sandhill Cranes fly in.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1999-02-11" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-02-11-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Probably Lunchtime Walk" date="1999-02-15" leader="Bill?" url="" filename-stem="1999-02-15-probably-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Saturday Stroll" date="1999-02-20" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-02-20-saturday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1999-03-05" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-03-05-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1999-03-18" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-03-18-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1999-03-23" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-03-23-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1999-03-30" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-03-30-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1999-04-09" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-04-09-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1999-04-22" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-04-22-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="1999-05-02" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-05-02-sunday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Saturday Stroll" date="1999-05-29" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-05-29-saturday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Trip" date="1999-05-30" leader="Mary and Bill?" url="" filename-stem="1999-05-30-sunday-trip"></trip>
<trip name="Ashland Pre-trip" date="1999-06-02" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-06-02-ashland-pre-trip"></trip>
<trip name="Ashland Pre-Trip" date="1999-06-03" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-06-03-ashland-pre-trip"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1999-06-28" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-06-28-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1999-07-22" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-07-22-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Wisconsin Trip" date="1999-07-29" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-07-29-wisconsin-trip"></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="1999-08-08" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-08-08-sunday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Ashland Trip" date="1999-08-19" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-08-19-ashland-trip"><notes><p>we stopped at Lower Klamath NWR and also Tule Lake NWR.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="1999-09-05" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-09-05-sunday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Golden Gate Audubon Trip" date="1999-09-26" leader="Mark Eaton" url="http://home.pacbell.net/mweaton/Birding/RareBirds/Philadelphia%20Vireo.html" filename-stem="1999-09-26-golden-gate-audubon-trip"><notes><p>The highlight of this trip was, of course, the philadelphia vireo. Mark has posted some interesting notes on his web site, detailing his further observations of this bird just days after he took us to see it.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Saturday Stroll" date="1999-10-23" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-10-23-saturday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1999-10-26" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-10-26-lunchtime-walk"><notes><p>Almost high tide</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1999-11-11" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-11-11-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Point Reyes Expedition 1" date="1999-11-13" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-11-13-point-reyes-expedition-1"></trip>
<trip name="Point Reyes Expedition 2" date="1999-11-14" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-11-14-point-reyes-expedition-2"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="1999-11-19" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-11-19-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="1999-12-12" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-12-12-sunday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="San Jose Christmas Bird Count" date="1999-12-19" leader="Audubons" url="http://www.scvas.org/counts.html" filename-stem="1999-12-19-san-jose-christmas-bird-count"><notes><p>another reference url: http://birdsource.tc.cornell.edu/cbcdata/</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Icy Birding with the Parents" date="1999-12-27" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="1999-12-27-icy-birding-with-the-parents"></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="2000-01-02" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2000-01-02-sunday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="2000-01-09" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2000-01-09-sunday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="2000-02-06" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2000-02-06-sunday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Coastal Trip" date="2000-03-04" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2000-03-04-coastal-trip"><notes><p>with John Brewer and Stacy O'Leary</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Birding with Parents" date="2000-03-10" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2000-03-10-birding-with-parents"><notes><p>Mom and Dad were along for this trip during their visit to California</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Birding with Parents 2" date="2000-03-11" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2000-03-11-birding-with-parents-2"></trip>
<trip name="Birding with Parents 3" date="2000-03-12" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2000-03-12-birding-with-parents-3"></trip>
<trip name="Coastal Outing" date="2000-04-02" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2000-04-02-coastal-outing"></trip>
<trip name="Santa Clara Audubon Walk" date="2000-05-13" leader="Al Eisner" url="" filename-stem="2000-05-13-santa-clara-audubon-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Coastal Trip" date="2000-06-10" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2000-06-10-coastal-trip"></trip>
<trip name="Reactivity Offsite" date="2000-06-19" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="2000-06-19-reactivity-offsite"><notes><p>I saw a Western Whiptail lizard, a Rabbit, and some other mammal.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Saturday Stroll" date="2000-07-08" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2000-07-08-saturday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="2000-07-30" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2000-07-30-sunday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Wisconsin Trip" date="2000-08-04" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2000-08-04-wisconsin-trip"><notes><p>We saw two fauns wandering across the trail. Mary saw a Pileated Woodpecker; Bill did not.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Early Morning Airport Run" date="2000-08-26" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2000-08-26-early-morning-airport-run"><notes><p>We took Pat to the SF airport at something like 5:30am, and just kept on going. We got to Bolias at around 7:30am. We visited the Bolinas Lagoon, and also stopped at Point Reyes Bird Observatory. We even ate breakfast in Bolinas, a town that didn't seem to want us very much.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Early Morning Airport Run" date="2000-08-26" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2000-08-26-early-morning-airport-run"><notes><p>We took Pat to the SF airport at something like 5:30am, and just kept on going. We got to Bolias at around 7:30am. We visited the Bolinas Lagoon, and also stopped at Point Reyes Bird Observatory. We even ate breakfast in Bolinas, a town that didn't seem to want us very much.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="2000-08-27" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2000-08-27-sunday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Santa Clara Audubon Walk" date="2000-09-24" leader="Frank Vanslager" url="" filename-stem="2000-09-24-santa-clara-audubon-walk"><notes><p>The famous Gail C. accompanied us on this trip. Also, two attendees got into a heated discussion about the wingbars on Lesser versus American Goldfinches in non-breeding plumage.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Columbus Day Trip" date="2000-10-06" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2000-10-06-columbus-day-trip"></trip>
<trip name="Columbus Day Trip 2" date="2000-10-09" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2000-10-09-columbus-day-trip-2"></trip>
<trip name="Coastal Outing" date="2000-11-05" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2000-11-05-coastal-outing"></trip>
<trip name="Visiting Michelle and Brian" date="2000-11-12" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2000-11-12-visiting-michelle-and-brian"><notes><p>We saw a jackrabbit, a turtle, and a possible muskrat</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Wings over High Tide" date="2001-01-10" leader="Steve Shunk and Terry Steele" url="http://www.lovethembirds.com/wbc_home.htm" filename-stem="2001-01-10-wings-over-high-tide"><notes><p>Our first episode in a trilogy of three birding marathons in five days. We saw a skunk and a jackrabbit.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Wings over Panoche" date="2001-01-13" leader="Steve Shunk and Terry Steele" url="http://www.lovethembirds.com/wbc_home.htm" filename-stem="2001-01-13-wings-over-panoche"></trip>
<trip name="Wings over Merced" date="2001-01-14" leader="Steve Shunk and Terry Steele" url="http://www.lovethembirds.com/wbc_home.htm" filename-stem="2001-01-14-wings-over-merced"><notes><p>0700 to 0930</p><p></p><p>On the road from San Jose to Los Banos we started seeing raptors as soon as we got south of town and off the major highways. Our first serious stop was the rest area on highway 152, which yielded the Greater Road Runner we had been looking for in Panoche on the previous day. We also had nice looks through the scope at waterfowl far below on the reservoir.</p><p></p><p>1000 to 1100</p><p></p><p>We stopped in Los Banos for a pit stop and then headed toward the Merced National Wildlife Refuge (NWR). We didn't even exit the McDonald's parking lot before seeing over a dozen Cattle Egrets, our second life bird of the day. We spotted quite a few raptors on power poles and other birds on fences while en route to the NWR.</p><p></p><p>1100 to 1400</p><p></p><p>We spotted a wonderful Great Horned Owl just as we turned into the Merced NWR on our way to the parking lot. After pausing to look over the water from the parking lot, we slowly wound our way through the auto tour route, using walkie-talkies to relay information back and forth between cars. Although we didn't see the vast flocks of geese and cranes one might hope for, we did see some excellent ducks and raptors.</p><p></p><p>1400 to 1630</p><p></p><p>We decided to try our luck at the nearby San Luis NWR, where another auto tour route took us right past a lovely American Bittern. Some stubborn folks tracked a high altitude soaring raptor, which turned out to be a Bald Eagle.</p><p></p><p>1630 to 1700</p><p></p><p>We decided to squeeze in one last stop at the San Joaquin dam, where we enjoyed the sunset and scanned our scopes across the water. A restful end to a very full day.</p><p></p><p>Throughout the day we saw some excellent mammals and farm creatures, including:</p><p></p><p>coyote - healthy and happy looking 20 feet from the car </p><p>vole - not so healthy - he was being eaten and swallowed whole by a great egret. Great show. Wish we had it on tape to watch agan and again.</p><p>cows - Cows, cows, cows </p><p>emu - just one. Must be an experiment or a pet. </p><p>sheep - several breeds intermixed, but mostly looked like eatin' sheep, not spinnin' sheep </p><p>sheepdog - you never saw a happier animal </p><p>house cat - with dark shoulders and a white breast, sitting right where we expected to find hawks. It's always funny when you're trying to turn a mammal into some specialty bird.</p><p></p><p></p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Saturday Stroll" date="2001-02-03" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-02-03-saturday-stroll"><notes><p>I was out wandering while Mary was at a conference; lovely weather!</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="2001-02-04" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-02-04-sunday-stroll"><notes><p>Mary and I met up after her conference ended; we worked on identifying gulls and grebes.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Work at Home" date="2001-02-07" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-02-07-work-at-home"></trip>
<trip name="Soggy Presidents Day" date="2001-02-19" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-02-19-soggy-presidents-day"><notes><p>Really raining pretty hard, didn't see much, but had a good time.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Birding with Erik" date="2001-03-03" leader="Erik Andersen" url="" filename-stem="2001-03-03-birding-with-erik"><notes><p>Michelle, Brian, Mary, Bill, and Erik tour the Sonoma State University Campus</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Work at Home" date="2001-03-08" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-03-08-work-at-home"><notes><p>All the feeders were empty this morning; I refilled all of them; the birds showed up about an hour after the refill.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Work at Home" date="2001-03-16" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-03-16-work-at-home"></trip>
<trip name="March Madness" date="2001-03-17" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-03-17-march-madness"><notes><p>Sitting around,watching Missouri play a tough game against Duke.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Big Sur Weekend 1" date="2001-03-23" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-03-23-big-sur-weekend-1"><notes><p>We saw 2-5 humpback whales close to the shore -- flukes, backs, spouts, and one breech. It was very cool.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Big Sur Weekend 2" date="2001-03-24" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-03-24-big-sur-weekend-2"></trip>
<trip name="Weekend Stroll" date="2001-04-01" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-04-01-weekend-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="2001-04-29" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-04-29-sunday-stroll"><notes><p>part of bill's birthday weekend.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Backyards of Illinois" date="2001-05-26" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-05-26-backyards-of-illinois"></trip>
<trip name="Champaign Audubon Walk" date="2001-05-27" leader="Beth Chato" url="" filename-stem="2001-05-27-champaign-audubon-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Lost Coast 1" date="2001-06-16" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-06-16-lost-coast-1"></trip>
<trip name="Lost Coast 2" date="2001-06-17" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-06-17-lost-coast-2"></trip>
<trip name="Morro Bay 1" date="2001-07-16" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-07-16-morro-bay-1"><notes><p>Went to Morro Rock</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Morro Bay 2" date="2001-07-17" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-07-17-morro-bay-2"><notes><p>Went to Hearst Castle, then across to Hearst San Simeon Memorial Beach</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Morro Bay 3" date="2001-07-18" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-07-18-morro-bay-3"></trip>
<trip name="Morro Bay 4" date="2001-07-19" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-07-19-morro-bay-4"><notes><p>Walked to the Elfin Forest. Went to Morro Strand State Beach; visited an artificial wetlands next to a housing development called the Cloisters</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Morro Bay 5" date="2001-07-20" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-07-20-morro-bay-5"></trip>
<trip name="Morro Bay 6" date="2001-07-21" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-07-21-morro-bay-6"></trip>
<trip name="Bottom of the Bay Checking 1" date="2001-07-28" leader="Mary and Bill" url="http://www.scvas.org/publicat.html" filename-stem="2001-07-28-bottom-of-the-bay-checking-1"><notes><p>Mary and Bill go to check two entries in the SCVAS "Birding at the Bottom of the Bay"</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Bottom of the Bay Checking 2" date="2001-07-29" leader="Mary" url="http://www.scvas.org/publicat.html" filename-stem="2001-07-29-bottom-of-the-bay-checking-2"><notes><p>Mary went by herself to check Rancho San Antonion and Stevens Creek County Park while Bill was rehearsing</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Bottom of the Bay Checking 3" date="2001-08-05" leader="Mary and Bill" url="http://www.scvas.org/publicat.html" filename-stem="2001-08-05-bottom-of-the-bay-checking-3"><notes><p>We stopped at the Saratoga Wildwood park and Hakone Gardens</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Hiking with Phil" date="2001-08-18" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-08-18-hiking-with-phil"><notes><p>This was also a Birding at the Bottom of the Bay book checking trip. We had a great time walking around with house guest Phil Kohlmetz</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Bottom of the Bay Checking 4" date="2001-09-03" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-09-03-bottom-of-the-bay-checking-4"></trip>
<trip name="Trial Run for Big Day" date="2001-09-15" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-09-15-trial-run-for-big-day"></trip>
<trip name="Big Day California Fall Challenge" date="2001-09-23" leader="Dick Carlson" url="" filename-stem="2001-09-23-big-day-california-fall-challenge"><notes><p>Mary and Bill teamed up with Dick Carlson to do this trip as a fund-raiser for the San Francisco Bay Bird Observatory. It is our largest single day species total ever. Here's how the day unfolded:</p><p></p><p>4:45am Clock radio turns on. Ugh.</p><p></p><p>4:50am Alarm clock goes off. Ugh.</p><p></p><p>5:00am Found the list I wrote myself last night about what to do this morning, with helpful items like "feed cat" and "eat breakfast"</p><p></p><p>5:30am On our way to Dick's house</p><p></p><p>6:00am We're in Dick's car, headed for the coast. The new plan is to hit the coast first, then work back toward the bay side.</p><p></p><p>6:45am In the pre-dawn overcast we spot our first species -- a Great Horned Owl posing out in the open on a telephone wire. It seems an auspicous start to the day.</p><p></p><p>7:30am, Pigeon Point Lighthouse. A huge raft of Common Murres floats serenely as dozens of cormorants speed by. No warblers in the trees near the hostel.</p><p></p><p>8:20am On the way to Gazos Creek we spot our first of eight or ten Red-shouldered Hawks for the day.</p><p></p><p>9:00am, Gazos Creek Road. We've hit the warbler jackpot! These trees are teeming with chickadees, vireos, warblers. After much debate, we decide that we're seeing both Warbling and Philadelphia Vireo.</p><p></p><p>10:00am, Ano Neuvo State Park. Dick leads us in the secret back way to a beach overlook were we are greeted by one of the largest flocks of Western and Clark's Grebes any of us can remember.</p><p></p><p>11:00am On our way to Pescadero Beach, we pull of the road to look at a raptor, and notice a dozen Tricolored Blackbirds posing conveniently on the telephone wire directly overhead.</p><p></p><p>11:40am Immediately upon setting up the spotting scope at Pescadero Beach, eight mergansers hove into view around a bend in the creek. We decide its lunch time.</p><p></p><p>1:00pm We've finished lunch at Duarte's in Pescadero, and are much revived by the Cream of Artichoke Soup. We've seen over sixty species before lunch, and are feeling good about hitting our goal of one hundred species today. Before returning to Pescadero Marsh, we drive around the town itself. During a brief roadside stop, Mary and Bill see their first Pygmy Nuthatch. A local birder invites to stop by her delightful garden, where we get great looks at Say's Phoebe.</p><p></p><p>2:30pm, Pescadero Marsh. There are only four kinds of ducks here, but we've also rounded out our list of herons and egrets.</p><p></p><p>3:00pm Mezza Luna. Dick introduces to the famous "Mezza Luna Willows" behind the restraurant in Princeton-by-the-Sea. These trees, like the ones at Gazos Creek, are teeming with life.</p><p></p><p>4:00pm, Pillar Point Harbor. Finally, some Terns! We add Elegant Tern and Surf Scoter to the list and decide to head back over the hills.</p><p></p><p>5:30pm, Redwood Shores Radio Towers. Dick is right, this pond is amazing at high tide. Amongst hundreds of Godwits, Dowitchers, and Curlews, Dick shows Mary and Bill their first Red Knot outside of the Monterey Bay Aquarium aviary. We also enjoy great looks at Pectoral Sandpiper.</p><p></p><p>6:15pm Another unlikely but crowded pond is located directly behind the Silicon Valley Athletic Club. We add American White Pelican to the list.</p><p></p><p>7:00pm As the sunlight fades, we stop at the East Palo Alto Baylands, one of Dick's favorite bicycle destinations. We round out our list at 115 species with the distinctive calls of Clapper Rail and Sora.</p><p></p><p>What a day!</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Birding with Hilary" date="2001-09-30" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-09-30-birding-with-hilary"><notes><p>We rarely actually spot birds in the Redwoods; this time we saw several townsend's warblers, which was really cool.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Return to Shearwater" date="2001-10-27" leader="Debra Shearwater" url="" filename-stem="2001-10-27-return-to-shearwater"><notes><p>Our return to Monterey Bay and Shearwater Journeys was a smashing success. We left the dock at 8:00am and returned 3:30pm. In addition to four life birds, we saw an amazing number of marine mammals:</p><p></p><p>Blue Whale, California Sea Lion, Harbor Seal,  Sea Otter, Pacific White-sided Dolphin,Northern Right Whale Dolphin, Ocean Sunfish, Blue Shark, Northern Elephant Seal.</p><p></p><p>The ocean was glassy, the weather was cool and dry, the trip leaders were friendly and informative.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Birding with Matt and April" date="2001-11-03" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-11-03-birding-with-matt-and-april"><notes><p>We stopped first at Moss Landing, then walked around near the Aquarium. The weather was wonderful. Matt was very observant, and spotted several birds we would have missed.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Trees with Matt and April" date="2001-11-04" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-11-04-trees-with-matt-and-april"><notes><p>We saw a record eleven banana slugs on this hike!</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Coffee Run" date="2001-11-05" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-11-05-coffee-run"><notes><p>Graham and Dan thought these bird names were pretty funny</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Coffee Run" date="2001-11-09" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-11-09-coffee-run"></trip>
<trip name="Santa Clara Audubon Trip" date="2001-11-10" leader="Audubon" url="" filename-stem="2001-11-10-santa-clara-audubon-trip"></trip>
<trip name="Flood Day" date="2001-11-12" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-11-12-flood-day"></trip>
<trip name="Coffee Run" date="2001-11-15" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-11-15-coffee-run"></trip>
<trip name="Thanksgiving in Merced" date="2001-11-23" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-11-23-thanksgiving-in-merced"></trip>
<trip name="Visiting Ted" date="2001-11-24" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-11-24-visiting-ted"></trip>
<trip name="Coffee Run" date="2001-11-28" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-11-28-coffee-run"></trip>
<trip name="Coffee Run" date="2001-11-30" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-11-30-coffee-run"></trip>
<trip name="Coffee Run" date="2001-12-03" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-12-03-coffee-run"></trip>
<trip name="Coffee Run" date="2001-12-10" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-12-10-coffee-run"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Stroll" date="2001-12-11" leader="Mike and Mary" url="" filename-stem="2001-12-11-lunchtime-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="San Jose Christmas Bird Count" date="2001-12-16" leader="Mary and Bill and Rich and Bracey" url="" filename-stem="2001-12-16-san-jose-christmas-bird-count"></trip>
<trip name="Christmas Owling" date="2001-12-27" leader="John and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-12-27-christmas-owling"></trip>
<trip name="Calero Christmas Bird Count" date="2001-12-29" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2001-12-29-calero-christmas-bird-count"><notes><p>Count data: wesgre 1 amwpel 3 doccor 44 grbher 1 greegr 1 cangoo 9 mallar 47 gadwal 5 rudduc 19 funky duck 16 funky geese 10 gwfgoo 1 turvul 4 whtkit 1 coohaw 1 reshaw 2 rethaw 6 amekes 1 amecoo 160 ribgul 12 calgul 3 gull sp 323 rocdov 12 moudov 7 annhum 18 nutwoo 4 dowwoo 2 norfli 11 blkpho 7 saypho 1 stejay 4 wesjay 13 amecro 15 chbchi 13 oaktit 5 bushti 67 whbnut 4 ruckin 15 herthr 2 amerob 149 normoc 2 eursta 19 cedwax 20 yerwar 26 towwar 2 caltow 10 sonspa 4 whcspa 19 gocspa 52 daejun 27 houfin 19 lesgol 3</p><p></p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Coffee Run" date="2002-01-03" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-01-03-coffee-run"></trip>
<trip name="Saturday Stroll" date="2002-01-05" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-01-05-saturday-stroll"><notes><p>The weather was cool and cloudy, and the light was fading. It was quite cool.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Work At Home" date="2002-01-07" leader="Mary" url="" filename-stem="2002-01-07-work-at-home"></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="2002-01-13" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-01-13-sunday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="MLK Day with Steve" date="2002-01-21" leader="Steve" url="" filename-stem="2002-01-21-mlk-day-with-steve"><notes><p>We havd a lovely time driving from near Lawrence through the San Antonio valley, up the back side of Mount Hamilton, and down the familiar side past Grant Ranch. We inteded to stop at Lake Cunningham to look for a Lesser Black-Backed Gull, but the weather did not cooperate.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="2002-01-22" leader="Mary" url="" filename-stem="2002-01-22-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Wild Bird Center to the Coast" date="2002-01-25" leader="Steve" url="" filename-stem="2002-01-25-wild-bird-center-to-the-coast"></trip>
<trip name="Wild Bird Center to Point Reyes" date="2002-01-26" leader="Steve" url="" filename-stem="2002-01-26-wild-bird-center-to-point-reyes"><notes><p>also saw Black-tailed Jackrabbit and Black-tailed Mule Deer.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Wild Bird Center to High Tide" date="2002-01-27" leader="Steve" url="" filename-stem="2002-01-27-wild-bird-center-to-high-tide"><notes><p>Well, the Black Rail did not appear, disappointing approximately 80 birdwatchers in attendance for one of the highest high tides of the year. One couple we talked to had flown in from Minnesota to do some birdwatching, and scheduled their trip around this high tide.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Visiting Michelle and Brian" date="2002-02-02" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-02-02-visiting-michelle-and-brian"><notes><p>There was the spotted sandpiper, strolling along right next to the little restaurant. A lovely little park.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Coffee Run" date="2002-02-04" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-02-04-coffee-run"></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="2002-02-10" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-02-10-sunday-stroll"><notes><p>We worked on Ring-billed Gull versus other gulls at the duck pond. We also worked on distinguishing the Scaups.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="2002-02-17" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-02-17-sunday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Coffee Run" date="2002-02-26" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-02-26-coffee-run"></trip>
<trip name="Lunchtime Walk" date="2002-03-06" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-03-06-lunchtime-walk"></trip>
<trip name="Saturday Stroll" date="2002-03-09" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-03-09-saturday-stroll"><notes><p>We walked around with an out-of-town friend, admiring the Hooded Mergansers and talking about Harry Potter.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Saturday at the Zoo" date="2002-03-16" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-03-16-saturday-at-the-zoo"></trip>
<trip name="Malheur Spring Weekend 1" date="2002-04-19" leader="Steve Shunk" url="" filename-stem="2002-04-19-malheur-spring-weekend-1"><notes><p>[five years later, Bill returns to the scene of his 1997 solo drive up to Oregon and Malheur birding trip with Steve Shunk. This time, accompanied by an eagle-eyed Mary and a new spotting scope, promises to be even better.]</p><p></p><p>We awoke this morning in Kris and Steve's house outside of Sisters. They've got five acres at the end of several miles of dirt road, 30 chickens, 3 horses, a bunch of pine siskins at their feeders, and a stunning view of the three sisters mountains.</p><p></p><p>After a scrumptious breakfast of blueberry pancakes, bacon, and farm-fresh eggs, we headed west toward Bend and the Malheur refuge, After checking into the hotel around 4pm,. we drove around and looked at some flooded agricultural fields around town. We saw some impressive breeding behavior, including two pairs of curlews going at it, and three snipes trying out all the possible couplings. We found close to seventy species during the day, and it wasn't even a full day of looking.</p><p></p><p>We ate at a yummy thai restaurant that offers toast with it's Sate Chicken.</p><p></p><p>Tommorow we're going to get an early start.; the big question is, will we really get up early enough on day three to get to the Sage Grouse Lek before sunrise? Oy.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Malheur Spring Weekend 2" date="2002-04-20" leader="Steve Shunk" url="" filename-stem="2002-04-20-malheur-spring-weekend-2"><notes><p>An epic, twelve hour day of looking and listening. Good company, good snacks, almost no wind, great sunlight.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Malheur Spring Weekend 3" date="2002-04-21" leader="Steve Shunk" url="" filename-stem="2002-04-21-malheur-spring-weekend-3"><notes><p>We left the motel very early to get to the Lek by sunrise. After breakfast in Frenchglen we looked around the Page Springs campground and Double OO field station before driving back to Sisters. What an awesome trip!</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Mary explores San Mateo" date="2002-04-22" leader="Mary" url="" filename-stem="2002-04-22-mary-explores-san-mateo"></trip>
<trip name="Saturday Stroll" date="2002-05-04" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-05-04-saturday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="2002-05-05" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-05-05-sunday-stroll"><notes><p>Partly this was a trip for testing out  digital cameras with our new scope.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Tour of Don Edwards" date="2002-05-10" leader="Naturalist" url="" filename-stem="2002-05-10-tour-of-don-edwards"></trip>
<trip name="Saturday Stroll" date="2002-05-18" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-05-18-saturday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Work at Home" date="2002-05-22" leader="Bill and Mary" url="" filename-stem="2002-05-22-work-at-home"></trip>
<trip name="Pre-Ashland" date="2002-06-24" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-06-24-pre-ashland"></trip>
<trip name="Stroll in the Park" date="2002-06-26" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-06-26-stroll-in-the-park"></trip>
<trip name="Post Ashland" date="2002-06-29" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-06-29-post-ashland"></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="2002-08-18" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-08-18-sunday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Vacation Stroll" date="2002-08-19" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-08-19-vacation-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Post Ashland" date="2002-08-20" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-08-20-post-ashland"></trip>
<trip name="Anniversary Trip 1" date="2002-08-31" leader="Les Chibana" url="" filename-stem="2002-08-31-anniversary-trip-1"><notes><p>Although fog prevented us from finding the Condors, we had a great time looking around the coast and visiting the Big Sur Ornithological Station.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Anniversary Trip 2" date="2002-09-01" leader="Les Chibana" url="" filename-stem="2002-09-01-anniversary-trip-2"><notes><p>This was our first introduction to the Carmel River, and it proved to be a great spot for passerines.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Anniversary Trip 3" date="2002-09-02" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-09-02-anniversary-trip-3"></trip>
<trip name="Coffee Run" date="2002-09-04" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-09-04-coffee-run"></trip>
<trip name="Fall Challenge Kickoff" date="2002-09-14" leader="Jan Hintermeister" url="" filename-stem="2002-09-14-fall-challenge-kickoff"></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="2002-09-15" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-09-15-sunday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Humboldt Surf and Turf 1" date="2002-10-10" leader="Steve Shunk and Greg Gillson" url="" filename-stem="2002-10-10-humboldt-surf-and-turf-1"><notes><p>After grabbing lunch at the Felafel place across from the motel, we zoomed out to the marsh to try to watch shorebirds as the tide came in. We were a little late, but saw some excellent birds all the same.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Humboldt Surf and Turf 2" date="2002-10-11" leader="Steve Shunk and Greg Gillson" url="" filename-stem="2002-10-11-humboldt-surf-and-turf-2"><notes><p>We had some wonderful close encounters today -- waxwings, winter wrens, wrentits, hutton's vireo, all within a few feet at various times of the day. We worked a lot today on sounds.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="California Fall Challenge" date="2002-10-12" leader="Steve Shunk" url="" filename-stem="2002-10-12-california-fall-challenge"></trip>
<trip name="Humboldt Surf and Turf 4" date="2002-10-13" leader="Steve Shunk" url="" filename-stem="2002-10-13-humboldt-surf-and-turf-4"></trip>
<trip name="Church of Oka Ponds" date="2002-10-27" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-10-27-church-of-oka-ponds"></trip>
<trip name="Coffee Run" date="2002-11-11" leader="Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-11-11-coffee-run"></trip>
<trip name="Saturday Stroll" date="2002-11-16" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-11-16-saturday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="2002-11-17" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-11-17-sunday-stroll"><notes><p>Using instructions found in "Birding at the Bottom of the Bay", we explored parts of the park we'd never seen before.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Wine Tasting" date="2002-11-30" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-11-30-wine-tasting"></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Stroll" date="2002-12-01" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-12-01-sunday-stroll"></trip>
<trip name="Chrismas Bird Count" date="2002-12-15" leader="Mary and Bill, Bracey and Richard" url="" filename-stem="2002-12-15-chrismas-bird-count"></trip>
<trip name="Holiday Birding" date="2002-12-23" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-12-23-holiday-birding"></trip>
<trip name="Holiday Owling" date="2002-12-24" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-12-24-holiday-owling"><notes><p>many thanks to Champaign Audubon's Beth Chato for giving us detailed instructions on how to find this owl!</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Holiday Birding" date="2002-12-28" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2002-12-28-holiday-birding"><notes><p>at Meadowbrook Park</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Begin New Year Trip" date="2003-01-01" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2003-01-01-begin-new-year-trip"></trip>
<trip name="Sunday Rarity Chase" date="2003-01-05" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2003-01-05-sunday-rarity-chase"></trip>
<trip name="Wings over Panoche Valley" date="2003-01-11" leader="Steve Shunk" url="http://www.paradisebirding.com/sys-tmpl/door/" filename-stem="2003-01-11-wings-over-panoche-valley"><notes><p>We had lovely weather today driving around Panoche Valley and spotting birds against the emerald hills. The much sought-after Mountain Plover and Mountain Bluebird remained elusive, but we had many other excellent looks. Hawks were especially plentiful today, as were Say's Phoebes.</p><p></p><p>Birds we didn't see but were reported by others on the trip: Wrentit, California Gull, Vesper Sparrow, Turkey Vulture, Fox Sparrow.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Wings over San Joaquin Valley" date="2003-01-12" leader="Steve Shunk" url="" filename-stem="2003-01-12-wings-over-san-joaquin-valley"></trip>
<trip name="Playing Hooky" date="2003-01-16" leader="Mary and Bill" url="" filename-stem="2003-01-16-playing-hooky"></trip>
<trip name="Wings over Monterey" date="2003-01-18" leader="Steve Shunk" url="" filename-stem="2003-01-18-wings-over-monterey"><notes><p>The weather was fabulous, and we had four life birds today, which more than made up for the rare flycatcher we didn't see in Santa Cruz.</p></notes></trip>
<trip name="Wings over San Mateo" date="2003-01-19" leader="Steve Shunk" url="" filename-stem="2003-01-19-wings-over-san-mateo"></trip></tripset>
